Moissaye Marans Papers
Moissaye Marans Papers
1927-1965
Marans, Moissaye, 1902-1977
1 linear ft.
Spanning 1927 to 1965, the Moissaye Marans Papers comprises correspondence, artwork reproductions, writings, and memorabilia of the Roumanian-American sculptor (1902-1977). The collection focuses on the professional career, rather than the personal life, of the Jewish artist who specialized in religious subjects. Correspondence (1933-1964); artwork reproductions; and printed material, including articles and clippings (1927-1964), and exhibition catalogs(1939-1965).
149149
Biographical History
American Jewish sculptor, specialized in religious subjects. Born in Roumania.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Encompassing incoming letters and outgoing carbons, as well as a variety of printed material, the Correspondence-Subject Files (Boxes 1-2) makes up the bulk of the collection. Correspondents include fellow artists (Edmond Amateis, Enid Bell, Ralph Fabri, John Gregory, Willard Hirsch, Paul Manship, Henry Rox, Frederic Whitaker); authors (Philip Desind, Katharine Morrison McClinton, Raymond F. Piper); clergy (John Haynes Holmes); and politicians (Jacob K. Javits). Organizational correspondence includes that of museums (Jewish Museum, Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts); professional associations (Architectural League of New York, Audubon Artists, Inc., National Sculpture Society); patrons (Community Church of New York, Congregation Emanu El, First Presbyterian Church, Ridgewood Methodist Church, West Baden College); and publications (/Advance, Architectural Record, The Chicago Jewish Forum, The Church Woman/). Materials pertaining to the 1939 New York World's Fair and the United States Treasury Department document not only Marans' secular work, but also the relationship between government and the arts.
Artwork reproductions from various periodicals are arranged by sculpture title, while two pages of notes on his work constitute Marans' Writings (Box 2).
Memorabilia is composed entirely of printed material, which includes articles and clippings (1927-1964), as well as a number of exhibition catalogs (1939-1965).
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetical by type or title.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Sculptors; New York State; Marans, Moissaye, 1902-1977.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Artists, Jewish -- United States; Christian art and symbolism.; Jews, American.; Romanian Americans.; Sculptors -- United States.; Sculpture, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Exhibition catalogs.; Artists.; Sculptors.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Correspondence-Subject Files
  - Advance, 1954-1956 (Box 1)
  - Abingdon Press, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Amateis, Edmond, 1947 (Box 1)
  - American Jewish Tercentenary, See Jewish Museum (New York, N.Y.)
  - Architectural League of New York, 1950-1958 (Box 1)
  - Architectural Record, 1953 (Box 1)
  - Audubon Artists, Inc., 1954-1963 (Box 1)
  - Bell, Enid, 1957 (Box 1)
  - Brooklyn Association for Mental Health, Inc., 1957-1963 (Box 1)
  - Burdell, Edwin S., 1955-1956 (Box 1)
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace, 1951-1957 (Box 1)
  - Cecere, Gaetano, See National Sculpture Society
  - The Chicago Jewish Forum, 1955-1963 (Box 1)
  - The Church Woman, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Clay Club Sculpture Center, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - Community Church of New York, 1952-1963 (Box 1)
  - Congregation Emanu El (Houston, Texas), 1954-1959 (Box 1)
  - Congregational Christian Churches. Missions Council, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Desind, Philip, 1955 (Box 1)
  - Fabri, Ralph, 1956; 1963 (Box 1)
  - Fairmount Park Art Association, 1940-1949 (Box 1)
  - Family Guidance Center (Boston, Mass.), 1956 (Box 1)
  - First Presbyterian Church (Beloit, Wis.), 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - Gregory, John, 1954 (Box 1)
  - Hirsch, Willard, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Holmes, John Haynes, See Community Church of New York
  - Javits, Jacob K., 1959 (Box 1)
  - Jewish Museum (New York, N.Y.), 1947-1954 (Box 1)
  - Kitner, Harold, 1955 (Box 1)
  - McClinton, Katharine Morrison, 1956-1961 (Box 1)
  - Manship, Paul, 1954 (Box 1)
  - National Council of Jewish Women, 1958-1963 (Box 1)
  - National Sculpture Society, 1940-1964 (Box 1)
  - New York World's Fair, 1939, 1938-1942; undated (Box 1)
  - Pennsylvania Academy of the Fine Arts, 1941-1961 (Box 1)
  - Piper, Raymond Frank, 1947-1959; undated (Box 1)
  - Ridgewood Methodist Church (Ridgewood, N.J.), 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - Rox, Henry, 1953-1954 (Box 1)
  - Sculpture Center, See Clay Club Sculpture Center
  - Swarz, Sahl, See Clay Club Sculpture Center
  - United States. Post Office, See United States. Public Buildings Administration
  - United States. Public Buildings Administration, 1938-1944; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - United States. Treasury Department, See New York World's Fair, 1939 and United States. Public Buildings Administration (Box 1)
  - West Baden College (West Baden Springs, Ind.), 1950-1952 (Box 2)
  - Whitaker, Frederic, 1964 (Box 2)
  - Witherspoon, Margaret, 1958-1961; undated (Box 2)
  - World Council of Christian Education and Sunday School Association, 1951-1962 (Box 2)
  - A-Z, unidentified, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Artwork
  - Reproductions (by title) - A-Z, 2 folders (Box 2)
- Writings
  - Notes on work, undated (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Articles, undated (Box 2)
  - Clippings, undated (Box 2)
  - Exhibition catalogs, undated; 6 folders (Box 2)